If something gets in your way: flatten it.
The Phoenician Scheme is a comedy, adventure,
crime film directed by Wes Anderson.
Wealthy businessman Zsa-zsa Korda appoints his only
daughter, a nun, as sole heir to his estate.
As Korda embarks on a new enterprise, they soon become the target of
scheming tycoons, foreign terrorists, and determined assassins.
Zsa-zsa Korda, played by Benicio del Toro.
Sister Liesl, played by Mia Threapleton.
Bjorn Lund, played by Michael Cera.
Prince Farouk, played by Riz Ahmed.
Leland, played by Tom Hanks.
Reagan, played by Bryan Cranston.
The Phoenician Scheme is a 2025 espionage black comedy thriller film produced, written
and directed by Wes Anderson from a story he conceived with Roman Coppola.
The film features an ensemble cast that includes Benicio del Toro, Mia Threapleton, Michael Cera, Riz Ahmed, Tom Hanks, Bryan Cranston,
Mathieu Amalric, Richard Ayoade, Jeffrey Wright, Scarlett Johansson, Benedict Cumberbatch, Rupert Friend, Hope Davis, F.
Murray Abraham, Charlotte Gainsbourg, Willem Dafoe, and Bill Murray.
It tells the story of a ruthless businessman (del Toro) as he seeks to reconcile with his estranged
daughter (Threapleton) and complete an ambitious infrastructure project in Phoenicia.
The film was produced internationally between the United States and Germany by Anderson's
company American Empirical Pictures and Steven Rales's company Indian Paintbrush.
Anderson talked about the film in June 2023 while promoting Asteroid City; he
said it had already been written before the 2023 WGA strike began.
That September, he revealed that del Toro and Cera were planned to join the cast, and
he hoped to begin filming soon after the 2023 SAG-AFTRA strike ended.
The rest of the cast signed on between January and June 2024.
Filming took place at Babelsberg Studio in Germany, between March
and June 2024, with cinematographer Bruno Delbonnel.
Frequent Anderson collaborator Alexandre Desplat returned to compose the score.
The Phoenician Scheme had its world premiere in the main competition of the Cannes Film Festival on May 18, 2025, and was released
theatrically in Germany by Universal Pictures on May 29, 2025, and in the United States by Focus Features on May 30, 2025.
The film received generally positive reviews.
The film explores themes of assassin, nun, espionage, family, plane crash.
The tone is lighthearted.